what is neuro hacking what is know
tropics you've probably heard this
thrown abouts over the past few years
women people are talking about I take no
topics and my brain is working on
another level I'm taking these smart
drugs with scored no tropics you've got
to check a mouse maybe you've heard this
in conversation but you don't quite know
what it is you don't quite know what no
tropics do maybe you don't even know
what neuro hacking means today we're
going to find out today we're going to
talk to the co-founder of neuro hacker
collective who takes a complex system
approach to medicine and well-being
science we're going to be talking about
all the toxins that are in your living
room and in your kitchen and in your
life how spending so much time indoors
is affecting your life and what we can
do about it so we're going to get geeky
we're going to be talking brain health
no tropics smart drugs mr. Daniel
schmuck tan very a great to have you
here on the show sir thanks for having
me fun to be here so let's uh let's dumb
this down to the very simple
what is neuro hacking neuro hacking is a
general term for any kind of applied
neuroscience applied neuro technology
for optimizing the nervous system
optimizing the mind brain interface for
various cognitive goals or
psycho-emotional goals primarily we
could also be talking about neural
hacking for kind of sensory motor no
purpose --is or anything that has
top-down neurologic control whether
that's aspects of Health and regulation
immune system longevity but when we talk
about neural hacking in kind of contra
distinction to the whole field of bio
hacking we're generally talking about
cognitive and psychomotor all tuning and
up regulation okay so to the uninitiated
what did you just say because it sounded
very interesting it sounded it sounded
very complex what does it mean
a nutshell tools for increasing
cognitive capability intelligence focus
memory etc and for increasing
psychological well-being awesome
okay what is preventing us from just
being naturally gifted in our
intelligence and and having an optimized
nervous system like what's going on
today in 2017 as we're recording this
that's preventing us from from you know
having that kind of optimum capability
mm-hmm a tremendous amount actually so
we if you look at our interface with the
modern technological built world and you
look at what our evolutionary biological
history is and you look at the places
where there's suboptimal interface
between those it's in almost every area
so whether it's eating food that came
from top soil where the agricultural
method had it deficient in
micronutrients trace minerals not where
even if you're eating the healthiest
food that you can get access to you have
fundamental nutrient deficiency and
those are the nutrients that make not
only all aspects of physiology function
but brain specifically or whether we're
looking at the biggest toxicity like the
volatile organic compounds that are in
paint and flooring and so much you know
carpet so much interior toxicity or
external environmental toxicity
organophosphates bp's phthalates you
know most of the organic most of the
toxins that we are exposed to and we'd
see study after study of breast milk in
mothers in the United States having two
hundred-plus petrochemicals those are
those petrochemicals are either in the
current disruptors or carcinogens or
neurotoxins they have a real effect and
then we also have pathogens we never had
before because of antibiotic resistance
because of the amount of global travel
because of pesticide resistance so as
you share the effects of artificial
lighting the effect of the amount of
time people spend in fix postural
positions of the fix eye focal lengths
to a screen so many of these things are
things that we can work with but our sub
optimal to the human condition that's
just on the physio
oh gee side on the psychology side most
people don't have the connection to
tribe that would have been part of the
in evolutionary biology of humans
feeling meaningfully connected to other
humans don't have a sense of connection
to meaning and purpose have a level of
stress from the worldview that they have
come in to and from the macroeconomic
system and maybe from other macro global
issues so all of these are stresses on
our physiology our psychology or nervous
system that are going to have a sub
optimal quality of life and performance
if we don't work with them mmm
it's fascinating you're talking about
you know the food we eat
probably the cleaning products we use in
our kitchen or bathroom staring at a
screen obviously I talk a lot about the
dangers of looking at too much
electronic light sitting down as well as
a great book called get up by James
Levine which talks about the problems of
humans sitting down so much and how
that's affecting us and then I assume
what you were talking about when you
were talking about emotional capability
was of course Dunbar's number of people
I think was about 150 or 160 people when
we used to be in tribes that was the
number but now it seems like even if we
can if we're connected to more than that
which would make you feel like you were
popular because you connected 250 people
it seems to suggest that actually you
become less happy the more people that
you know the more people that you're
connected to or the more people that you
have to keep up with so can we bris
break down each you want each one of
these things let's just look at the food
we eat for the time being like if I go
to Whole Foods down on Fairfax and Santa
Monica Boulevard in West Hollywood here
can I be sure that the foods I'm eating
from the salad bar at Whole Foods or the
kale or spinach I'm buying from the in
the plastic bags are going to be okay
for me or is what you're arguing saying
you know what chances are it's still
going to be pretty bad for you I don't
want people to feel hopeless or but
you're about to make us feel hopeless
I mean is buying food that is from a
farmers market or someplace that is
local fresh are going to be a lot better
than other sources
yes very likely is buying food that is
organic likely to have less pesticide
residue and maybe more trace mineral yes
those were worth doing now even in even
in organic crops well we still find
glyphosate another organophosphate
residue just because it's being sprayed
nearby yeah we tend up and as the
topsoil going to have the microbiota and
trace mineral density of what you know
an indigenous and primitive environment
would have no so what's better it is
still not ideal
and people aren't aren't going to be
eating the variety of foods they would
in a natural environment that are
seasonal and that are you know each
pulling different minerals out of the
soil nair and they are going to have an
increased need for certain nutrients
because of toxins and stresses of the
processing so what we're arguing is
basically we we don't have an involved
process for dealing with
organophosphates or glutathione pathway
or cytochrome p450 pathway none of those
pathways were were evolved for dealing
with petrochemicals do they weren't part
of our evolutionary environment and so
given that we have the exposure to those
things it's actually important and
beneficial to support our system to deal
with the world that happens to be in so
how do we ensure that we're eating the
best quality foods and what's the
practical way that we can do this
outside of someone foraging or having a
garden where they can really ensure that
themselves I would say farmers markets
are great because it's someone else
having a garden where you can learn
about the farmer learn about their
methods find one like well likely you
can get something there that is you know
less hours since it was harvested than
at a grocery store and outside of where
that's viable then going to local coops
and local health food stores is going to
be probably the best
usually viable option and then of course
understanding the different things that
are in there which is that not
everything in a health food store is
actually healthy and not everything
that's healthy for one person is for
someone else and is there one question
that we should ask our farmer at the
farmers market when we're about to buy
the kale or the spinach or the
strawberries of the bananas or the fruit
or whatever we're about to buy is there
one question we should be asking and one
answer we should be looking for to
ensure that we're giving ourselves the
best opportunity to get the healthiest
food we possibly can well you might have
one question being that you framed it
that way which I'd love to hear I I
would generally ask what what are their
growing processes and premises so I'd
want to get into how they enrich the
soil what kind of you know do they use
rock flowers do they use different kinds
of micro Rosia and you know Soylent
enrichments pesticides proximity to
other pesticides how long from when
they're harvested to get in obviously
the more one knows about anything the
better they can do to navigate that
space okay we're talking to Daniel
schmuck Tim burger who's the co-founder
of neuro hacker collective we're going
to talk to him a little bit about a
product that he has as well that's going
to help you with your with your brain
and give you brain nutrients I had a
yeah a cleaner come to my home just the
other day here in Los Angeles Daniel and
she was complaining that I didn't have
enough products in my in my apartment
for her to be able to clean with she
didn't bring her own products she she
you know came and was reliant on me and
she asked me for next time that she came
to buy products the name of which
escapes me I think it was Clorox or
something like that and it was clearly
like a bad chemical what product should
I be buying to clean my home or to make
available like what what kind of natural
products because it seemed like
everyone's like oh yeah I get this and
it's like these vicious chemicals which
are doing this it seemed like permanent
damage to our brains just for a little
bit of context ammonia
an amazing beautiful chemical right
chlorine is a beautiful molecule all of
the chemicals that we have developed I
mean DDT is a fascinating chemical right
and so the better living through
chemistry the problem was that we didn't
understand complex systems we didn't
understand whole systems and so we
understood one very narrow part of the
system we developed something that would
be good for that part of the system but
it had other effects those other effects
were called externalities we've started
to understand those externalities and
realize the problem of the externalities
on both the environment and our
physiology so you know most of the
Pharma meds are actually really
fascinating chemicals for the one
pathway they're affecting it's just that
they affect other stuff which is very
problematic so it's not that it's not
that late your ammonia or lime away
doesn't have some application where it's
possibly beneficial but we do want to be
conscientious of the fact that the those
chemicals have effects on biology that
even breathing them have effects on
biology after the fact and those are
they're not effects on biology that we
want to have unconsciously so you have
companies like seventh generation and
Heather's and things that people can get
even in the grocery store that are more
eco friendly both from their effect on
the environment and their effect on
humans in the environment where they're
clean and then you have some companies
that make really kind of high-tech
things with a high tech nature tech
cleaning products that can be very
effective with different essential oils
and saponified natural fatty acids and
so yeah I'm not I'm not affiliated with
any of the companies I'm about to
mention but seventh generation certainly
I have a couple of those products and
I'm glad that you said that because it
makes me feel good about buying them and
then there's honest the honest company
which is the company created by the
Hollywood actress Jessica Alba and are
you familiar with their products so the
honest company products healthy as
healthy as I can get as well Daniel I
have seen them and heard good things
about them but I can't speak to the
chemistry okay okay
you mentioned global travel how is
global travel
affecting our nervous system lots of
things I was speaking from the point of
view of pathogens which was before we
had global travel we had the pathogens
that would have been within a bio region
there would have been things that we had
evolved immune system and microbiome to
deal with well and when we travel we had
the possibility exposed to a lot more
pathogens that we don't have innate
immunity to deal with and so there's of
course beautiful things about our
ability to travel and get exposed to
other ways of looking at the world and
you know people world views but there
are there are other effects of that that
we have to be conscientious of and so
the answer of just more vaccines for
every place you go also has consequences
and so just these are if we have a
system that's going to be exposed to
more pathogens and pathogens that it
didn't evolve to deal with in recent
history well then again we just say
that's a place where we want to have
more immune system support just like
we'd want to have more detox system
support if were exposed to more reminyl
toxins let's find a lot just a couple of
other problems and then we'll get into
some possible solutions here staring at
a screen what are the problems with that
well beyond the backlighting and the
lumens and the specific kind of the
kelvins the specific kind of spectral
frequencies of light that I imagine your
listeners all understand quite well a
few other things that can be problematic
about it is that it's a fixed focal
length and so if I'm looking at a
computer that is 12 inches or 18 however
many inches from my face then the focal
length of my eyes for being able to
focus very close and very far is not
getting engaged and those are muscles
and in an evolutionary environment we
would have been not looking at a very
fixed focal length for all that much
time right we've been looking further
often seeing trees up close in the
process of that dynamic movement of the
eye musculature to be able to focus near
and far as part of what helps keep that
musculature healthy and prevent the kind
of vision loss that we consider so
natural with age it happened before
computer screens and books for us but
fixed focal ink for very long period of
time there's an easy solution for that
which is
every 15 minutes half an hour that
you're looking at a book or screen just
look far away you know and let your eyes
focus look at something very close that
your eyes focus so muscular stays
engaged there's also a postural effect
of if I'm looking at a screen if it
involves me not moving very much then of
course we have all of the neurological
myofascial affects of just being very
sedentary but if the posture if the
ergonomics themselves have been looking
down and taking the s-curve out of my
cervical spine the secret of my cervical
spine you know then I'm going to be
dealing with those postural effects so
computers are awesome International
Travel is awesome and to the degree that
we're interfacing with it for one set of
reasons but it's having other effects we
just want to understand those effects
and know how to augment any possible
negatives because I got a lifespan
treadmill desk and I'm as I'm recording
this with you now I'm standing on it I'm
not actually walking on it at the moment
that I I now for the most part work at a
computer standing up and initially I
thought I was so clever but then I
realized that I didn't have a computer
stand on my desk so my computer was
actually down at kind of chest level and
so my head was kind of you know aiming
down a little bit rather rather than
straight so here I was the months going
I'm so clever I'm on a treadmill desk
I'm standing up look at me and then I
was like oh actually hang on a second my
spine is probably still slouching over
because I'm looking down so now I have a
stand and stand my computer on my laptop
sits on top that's down and as you can
see I'm talking to you now Daniel my
eyes are at my head and my posture is
exactly the way it should be I'm
speaking to you from home on my couch on
a laptop so laptops are are pretty
profoundly suboptimal organ omits and as
much as we can say that we'd like people
on not on computers which is not
necessarily realistic for what the work
they have to do in the world it's also
meaningful or that we want them on organ
comically perfect computer setups which
when they're traveling is going to be
hard at least understanding the dynamics
or one can counterbalance them but for
most people the ergonomics that are
going to be important is
if you're looking straight ahead meaning
not down and not up you would like to be
looking slightly up from there if you're
going to be in one place for a long
period of time so that the natural C
curve in the cervical spine is being
supported rather than otherwise so we're
we're generally looking a little bit
down then we end up getting the muscles
in the back of the neck and the
suboccipital muscles getting tight
causing all of the kind of dynamics that
come from that and so if someone puts
their monitor higher than they normally
would where the center point of their
monitor is around eye level and then
they usually want their keyboard low and
we can get into ergonomic keyboards so
that the shoulders aren't up at that's
generally keyboard low monitor high is a
kind of first rule of thumb I love it
well I'm now you've inspired me to put
my computer up even higher now so I'm
going to make sure I do that when we
when we finish this interview thank you
for that for the tip there two more
things I want to talk about before we
move on to a little bit more about neuro
hacking but we're talking to Daniel
schmuck Tim Berger and you can check out
what he does over at Nero hacker comm
that's Nero hacker.com
you can read all about what it means to
be a neuro hacker Wi-Fi
I love Wi-Fi I would beware everywhere I
go now when I travel it's like I need
Wi-Fi I need Wi-Fi we're all addicted to
Wi-Fi when I was down in Sydney
Australia recently they've got free
Wi-Fi on Bondi Beach and when I was
traveling through the Baltic area and
Latvia Lithuania everywhere you go is
public Wi-Fi free everywhere I'm in my
apartment here in Los Angeles I've got
the super duper high speed Wi-Fi just
running through the whole place what are
the potential dangers of Wi-Fi and or
too much Wi-Fi this is a tricky and
harder to answer question when we think
about wireless transmission in general
so we're talking about EMF and RF so
we're looking at Wi-Fi we're looking at
Bluetooth we're also looking at 60 Hertz
EMF that is the AC in our house we're
looking at EMF fields from
raise motors etc what we're also looking
at police signal transmission military
signal you know other frequencies of
radio what we know is that the total
amount of wireless energy that people
are exposed to has been on the power law
like Moore's law since the 60s as we
have had more cell towers and more
satellites and more frequencies we are
doubling the amount of transmission that
we're exposed to something like every 18
months that means that we're in a very
high number of order of magnitudes more
total wireless transmission than we ever
were in an evolutionary environment that
that is going to have some physiologic
effect is pretty easy to buy that
basically when you measure EEG when you
measure EKGs you're measuring bio
signals and that there's actually
electrical signal processing that is how
we work the electrical signal processing
is core to how our nervous system works
that it's sensitive and that all signals
end up affecting all other signals
through wave interference exactly how it
affects us there's a lot of resources
conflicting on in different countries
have done research very differently
largely based on the how big telecom is
affecting the way their government does
research very much like you Pharma
effective you know government funding
research so we're actually doing a
meta-analysis and structured review of
all of the research done from all the
company all the countries in the world
right now on the topic of wireless
transmission and you know potential
cancer effects potential oxidative
effects of sub ionizing radiation in
humans and other biology so we actually
should have the best information on that
topic available soon but we still have a
lot of interpretation to do and when
you're doing meta-analysis where the
initial pieces of data that you're
looking at are questionable to begin
with it's tricky but I would say that
for people to be thoughtful
about their exposure is warranted and to
take easy steps like not keeping your
cell phone near your bed at night and
not having unlimited amounts of cell
phone and other access and turning your
Wi-Fi router off at night just the easy
steps one can do seem very well
warranted and anecdotally many people
who have left cities and went to places
where they had almost no wireless
exposure and deep wilderness describe
psycho neurodynamics especially sleep
issues but anxiety anorexia going away
now whether that just could being in
nature is beautiful whether it's the
stress of the city or smog and there's
so many factors that's close to
meaningless on its own but we also
notice a number of people who put
themselves inside the Faraday cages and
found much better sleep so I would say
that research wise we don't know fully
but there's good reason to think it's
something worth paying attention to is
it possible that 1020 years or two years
or whatever we're going to realize that
cell phones and Wi-Fi is going to be as
damaging to us as we now know that
smoking is is to us for years nobody
realized nobody thought that smoking was
bad for you and then all of a sudden in
the 50s and 60s it started to sort of
catch on or actually we're starting to
see some correlation here between
smoking and being unfair and heart
disease is it possible that one day not
so long from now or a long time from now
we're going to wake up and go damn I
cannot believe we were using the Wi-Fi
can't believe we're using cellphones we
were absolutely killing ourselves
entirely possible damn I would say that
it is probable that we will realize some
effects that seem unacceptable to us
with I'm not quantifying how much
compared to cigarettes but some of that
now cigarettes are pretty easy which is
we just don't actually need them right
Wi-Fi and just wireless energy
transmission and not just wireless but
energy transmission in general we're
just not going to go backwards from that
so I think one of the things that's
going to happen is we're going to
start realizing that just like you know
we're not going to stop having cleaning
products we're a make better cleaning
products where we pay attention to how
the molecules and the cleaning products
actually interface with biology I think
we're going to start paying attention to
understanding bio signals better and
what are the primary kind of EEG EKG
cellular signaling bio signals that are
most sensitive and starting to develop
wireless transmission thoughtfully in
terms of the spectral ranges that it
works in to how it will interface with
biology we're like Tesla hypothesized
that it could actually be a healing
force rather than a illness worse all
right let's do one more before we move
on to some talk about no tropics and I
want to talk about a little bit about
qualia which is a smart drug that you
have developed we're talking you talked
a little bit before about the emotional
feelings and the tribe and I mentioned
you know Dunbar's I think it was 150
people that's the tribe how are we how
are we struggling with having too many
Facebook friends or having being
connected to too many people like what's
what's going on here how is this
affecting affecting us so the
primatologist Dunbar took an observation
many people have had previously which is
that most indigenous tribes capped out
at around 150 people give or take maxed
out around 225 in a few cases but
generate hundred 50 and then if they got
bigger than that they would bifurcate or
intentionally limit their size and
there's a question as to why and he
found that there was a similar thing
that happened in all kinds of primates
and that the size of the troop they
could hold was actually proportional to
neocortical volume and the idea was that
we actually have a limited number of
unique relationships we can actually
process well and so when we've got about
150 people you can actually know
everybody in that village well know
their lives their history what's going
on and that works if you're going to
have a village where everyone is going
to impact everyone knowing everybody
caring about everybody being able to see
in real time
effect on them is part of what makes
social cohesion works as soon as you
start having enough people that you
actually can't track everybody then you
start having anonymous people and you
start having people where if they're
suffering you don't kind of care as much
and then you can have effects that could
lead to them suffering but you don't
care as much you can't have social
cohesion in the same way now obviously
we are not going to move back to a world
of just Dunbar number tribes because you
also then have to have technology that
only you know is back to the technology
of that time where you're only affecting
that number of people and obviously our
technology extends our impact to now
global there's and there's actually what
we can think of that was the first
insight there's multiple Dunbar numbers
which is numbers where different social
dynamics occur one on one is the first
right then small groups three four then
up to about 12 or 15 etc so it's really
not a problem how many people you've
been exposed to or how many people you
have friends on Facebook it there is a
need to have some deep meaningful
interactions with some number of people
which will probably be less than your
total number of friends on Facebook and
it's important to understand the
difference of in-person deep meaningful
human interactions where you deeply know
them they deeply know you and you can be
authentic with each other then the kinds
of interactions that are mediated by
over social media
so stop focusing on trying to get a
hundred thousand Instagram fans and
Facebook Likes and start really going in
and and and concentrating on the quality
of relationships rather than the
quantity it's in I really want to say
I'm a technologist hmm I am just about
right use of technology understanding
all of the effects of it I have nothing
wrong with someone getting a hundred
thousand likes on Facebook if they're
sharing a message that's meaningfully
benefiting the world and having more
people hear that that is actually making
a better world I just want them to
understand that that doesn't equal deep
interpersonal human connection and a
bunch of people liking them on facebook
also isn't going to give them a
meaningful sense of esteem it's going to
give them some quick external reference
dopamine hits they can cover up the fact
that something in their childhood didn't
teach them who they were and made them
externally
Firenze or for other people's approval
about who they are but it's not bad to
develop a following it just needs to be
for the right reason and if the reason
is self esteem or connection it's the
wrong tool for that job we're talking to
Daniel schmuck Tim burger the co-founder
of nero hector nero hacker I should say
collective Daniel what what are no
topics a lot of people ask me about this
in I don't actually have a very clear
answer but just explain to me what it
what exactly are no Tropics I'll make a
distinction between three different
terms that are often used kind of
synonymously but are worth defining
differently brain nutrients nootropics
and smart drugs so when we think of
brain nutrients we think about nutrients
it would be part of a natural diet that
are involved in healthy brain function
that either we might be deficient in or
that we can actually utilize more of and
it will you know meaningfully bolster
our capabilities so we're talking about
vitamins and minerals and antioxidants
here so to the degree that there are key
nutrients so when people are talking
about the effects of minerals like
magnesium or lithium or zinc or etc on
brain function or vitamin D or
phospholipids or essential fatty acids
those are all brain nutrients that one
would ideally get in a healthy diet but
because again like we said it's very
hard to get adequate amounts of those in
a healthy diet and we have increased
demand because say we're talking about B
vitamins we to the degree that you're
experiencing more psychological stress
than you would an evolutionary
environment you're going to burn through
B vitamins quicker so supplementing the
appropriate brain nutrients can be
useful the distinction there is that's
going to take you from deficiency to not
deficiency which means your normal
healthy baseline of cognitive and
psychological will be supported it's not
going to move you beyond baseline
capacity because those are elements that
are part of the evolutionary environment
right so smart drugs and the tropics are
distinct in that they are not nutrients
it would be part of a normal
they are some kind of additional set of
chemistry synthetic or natural that are
going to try and modulate some systems
for enhanced capability so no trophic
generally means a chemical that can
enhance some aspect of cognitive
function like memory or focus or
attention or verbal fluency or task
switching
so some nutrient that can modulate some
aspect of cognitive function beyond
someones normal healthy baseline without
meaningful side-effects that's the
general definition of a nootropic and
then a smart drug is usually and these
terms are don't have solid semantic
definitions they're they're kind of
slang terms but I'm going to give you
the best general definitions smart drugs
are usually pharmaceuticals that have
some cognitive benefit generally for
off-label purposes so these are either
psychiatric meds like a DD or Ritalin or
wellbutrin or narcolepsy meds like
modafinil or Alzheimer's meds or
Parkinson's meds levodopa things like
that that can increase wakefulness
increase focus
increase you know something smart drugs
can enhance some aspects of cognitive
function that someone wants experience
and you know hypothetically this could
be not just Pharma drugs but any drug
you could put Kourt rayon or
methamphetamine or
other drugs into those categories where
they do modulates some neurotransmitters
like dopamine in a way that will have
some cognitive effect but usually with
some meaningful side-effects immediate
side-effects like they might up regulate
focus but increase anxiety or paranoia
or irritability or something like that
and they might also have long-term side
effects which could be anything from
like real physiological issues to patta
toxicity or something but also just
dependence right addiction forming
because
they're taking something like dopamine
or acetylcholine or glutamate or some no
transmitter usually that your body
naturally regulates and they're
overriding the natural regulatory
process to spike it and in doing so if
you do that enough times can actually
override the natural regulatory process
where it becomes dependent on that
exogenous input that's what we call
addiction no tropics the goal with no
tropics and it's why it's like kind of a
normal cycle magic unicorn idea is that
there are some chemistry's that can be
added to the system that can enhance
some aspect of function without creating
meaningful short-term or long-term side
effects so of all so obviously the way
that you're describing it nootropics
improves your cognitive function above
your average functionality without the
side-effects smart drugs if we are to
take your explanation is are can also
improve cognitive effect and they're
good things like a DD and Alzheimer's
but they come with problems they come
with potential short and long term
effects and I think there was a third
one their brain nutrients right I think
you broke it into can just explain brain
nutrients again as opposed as that is
different from the smart drugs and the
no topics essential fatty acids
essential amino acids vitamins minerals
antioxidants the things that you would
normally get from food that either
you're not getting enough of from food
or that it's beneficial to get
additional amounts of based on what you
know what we're exposed to how much
we're actually using our brains and the
cognitive load so these are basically
brain nutrients are either going to be
things that could be found in food or
things that could be found endogenously
in the body that the body would make
from food gotcha okay so you're
obviously a proponent of no tropics of
all those three correct and brain
nutrients but not so much with the smart
drugs
well again like I said bleach has a
right application man any drug can have
a right application but in general there
is such a
there is such a profound complexity to
how human physiology works and complex
means something different than
complicated the circuit chip is
complicated it was designed externally
you put a certain number of transistors
linked one particular way a cell is
complex it's self-organizing its
boundary is non arbitrary complex
systems behave in fundamentally
different in it and more organizing
dynamic kind of ways in complicated
systems so when we look at human
physiology and especially the brain it's
such a radically complex self-organizing
a dynamic homeostatic system that we
don't want to override that right so if
someone's dopamine is low our goal isn't
to just give them insane dopamine or a
dopamine agonist it would be safe to say
well let's see if we can understand the
dopaminergic system better and see how
to support that systems endogenous
regulatory capacity so that the
intervention that we're doing actually
leads to lasting up regulation rather
than short-term stimulus and then
lasting down regulation so in general
for all kinds of inputs to biology I'm
interested in things that understand and
that seek to better understand the
body's natural dynamic homeostatic
processes and seek to work with and up
regulate them rather than override them
gocha ok so let's go back to neuro
hacker collective which is the
organization that you that you
co-founded what is its purpose what is
its mission and what is unique about its
approach to neuro hacking and applied
psycho neuro-ophthalmology agnostic
meaning biochemical technologies that's
both direct-to-consumer like neutral
and nutriceuticals as well as things
that could be you know doctor mediated
for medical conditions and general
things there direct-to-consumer are
going to be and neuro hacking the way we
think of it usually is not for curing
illness but for optimization well-being
support and enhancement but a complexity
approach and assistance biology approach
to medicine is also very meaningful part
of the deeper research that were
involved in but so you know we work with
biochemical solutions we work with
microbiome ik solutions were interested
in genomic solutions and neuro tech
transcranial lasers transcranial direct
stimulation currents you know ultrasound
EEG neurofeedback as well as
psychotherapeutic and you know
meditative technologies working with the
human hardware and software we're
interested in anything that basically
can up regulate some aspects of human
experience to the betterment experience
or human capacity for any kind of
personal condition and the reason why
this is so meaningful for us is all of
the other issues that we care about in
the world beyond human experience and
capacity are affected by human
experience and capacity all the major
problems that we see environmentally and
socially etc are caused by human
activity and the solutions need to come
about through human activity so
upgrading the comprehensive collective
intelligence of humanity not just
cognitive intelligence but interpersonal
intelligence you know etc ends up being
a meaningful lever for every other thing
we're still to that extent you've
created your own products called qualia
qu al I a and I'm presuming this is an O
tropic right yes so tell us a little bit
about what this is like what so tell us
a little bit about why qualia is a
little different and what typical
experiences people might have if they
take this product that you've created so
like I said we're working in a lot of
different areas of technology quality is
the first product that we have brought
to market we have quite a few other
products
trials that will be coming to market
this year and then some relatively
difficult ones it will take a little bit
longer but are developing well the goal
with qualia was when we look at the give
or take 15 billion dollars a year
domestically in energy drinks and how
much kind of caffeine stimulus happens
and if we look at the estimated
something like 5 billion dollars an
off-label adderall use not justified
doctor adderall use which we can
question if is ever a good thing but
just people who are their midterms or
finals or tech startup whatever seeking
that kind of enhancement because there
is a increased demand for productivity
and cognitive productivity beyond what
there's ever been well having more
things trying to distract from focus and
you know also stresses on the nervous
system like we've talked about the thing
about adderall and other smart drugs and
just tons of caffeine is that while
they can positively affect some metrics
which is why people use them many of the
other metrics that are critical are
actually being down regulated in real
time so we can see for most people when
they're taking adderall that their focus
will go up their drive will go up but
certain aspects of creative thinking and
systemic thinking and even aspects of
memory go down let alone emotional
things like empathy going down and then
long-term health effects so we wanted to
see can we develop something that would
meet the same need people's desire to be
able to go into creative productive flow
states where their full cognitive
capabilities were available can we do
that more comprehensively than has been
done so far and more safely and we
started by doing this in integrative
clinical settings where we were running
people's whole genome we were running a
lot of clinical chemistry were running
brain scans were giving medical history
and we were really dialing in custom
personalized chemistry for people then
the question was could we take some
elements of that that would work across
a bell curve of people and and
meaningfully be able to affect them
because personalized chemistry at scale
is tricky we're work
we're actually working on moving from
the one version of qualia to multiple
versions in the future all the way to
you know lab based fully customized
chemistry pharmacology but we were
really surprised at how well we were
able to do taking a systems approach to
no traffic swear we were you know we
started out by modeling when people are
taking some smart drug or something to
that effect what are they really seeking
and we did kind of a cognitive science
of their they're seeking increased
short-term memory and long-term memory
and speed of memory and digit span and
verbal fluency and task switching and
creative thinking and critical thinking
you know analysis and synthesis and a
bunch of emotional things like emotional
resilience and drive and you know so we
were looking at that whole set of things
together and then saying alright we want
to be able to affect that whole set not
a subset of it and then what are the
underlying physiologic pathways that
mediate all that which ones are mediated
via a single colon or glutamate or
catecholamines or ion channels or so we
map that out used kind of systems
dynamics for looking at how those all
interact with each other and the and the
pathways that regulate them and then
looked at the chemistry that maps to
those and then started our kind of
hypothesis development process for what
we could do to upregulate
all of those systems simultaneously in a
way that would actually up regulate the
regulatory capacity of the system where
after someone had been on it for a while
rather than get addicted and
downregulated it could actually have
lasting baseline elevation so let's just
say I take I take qualia what's my first
week going to be like what's a typical
experience of someone who uses qualia in
the first week and then you know second
third and you know short-term and in
long-term so we have done a bunch of
internal you know single blinded trials
we were just engaged in their first
double-blind of trials right now but we
don't have results I can't make any
claim about what one will experience I
can say what many people have claimed
and many people is quite large numbers
for us
now and obviously it's going to be
different experiences for different
people I want to say first quality is
actually not recommended for everyone
there are contraindications specifically
if people are on psychiatric meds or
neurologic meds or treating cancer or
treating hypertension then we would not
recommend people use it without
consulting their appropriate health care
practitioner first this doesn't mean
that there are not healthcare
practitioners that are using it and
recommending it for such people in
knowledgeable ways we wouldn't recommend
people do it on their own because there
are chances of interactions so that said
for people that it's not contraindicated
we're getting an extremely high positive
success rate this the small percentage
of people about 16% of people that
describe an annul effect they don't
experience very much are almost
exclusively because they have sleep
issues if people are not getting
adequate Delta sleep so if they're not
sleeping enough or not sleeping well
quality will usually not work well for
them because memory consolidation
happens during Delta sleep and we're
specifically working with chemistry that
is mediated through the memory
consolidation pathways so one of the
things we say is you know that it's that
it really is critical that people are
sleeping well and if you have AB Nia or
not Tori or something like that probably
going to need to address that first of
the people who are using it having good
experiences there testimonials on the
website that increased focus attention
concentration insight actual emotional
steadiness emotional regulation many
people describing increased epiphany
increased empathy all of those things
are fairly common
alright we're talking to Daniel schmuck
Tim Berger co-founder of neuro hacker
collective I just had a look on your
website while we were talking there and
I see a couple of testimonials of people
that I actually know as Eric Utley and
TJ Anderson there's a few people there
are no live down the San Diego area if
you're listening to this and you want to
follow the work of neuro
a collective there is a Facebook page
called neuro hacker collective you could
go and like that page and be kept up to
date with everything at daniel
trachtenberg ER and his team are doing
in terms of emotional resilience tropics
outsmarting the modern world as we've
been talking about is there anywhere
else where our listeners can find you
Daniel knew or else you'd like us to go
I think the Facebook page in the website
are good resources right now if you go
to the website you'll get a hint on the
ethos page of what we're working on
beyond what our current offering is but
mostly you'll see information about
quality and there's a decent bit of
information about the chemistry and the
scientific approach that we use and you
know there's information that's worth
looking at the blog has some very
interesting articles but what we're
really working towards is being able to
vet all of the different technologies
that can meaningfully enhance people's
psychology and cognition this is
everything from psychotherapeutic
technologies to psychedelic assisted
psychotherapy - you know all forms of
neuro tech really betting which ones are
effective and that are effective not
just at short-term and partial effects
but positive system up regulation and
then effective for what for what kinds
of people for what kinds of pathway
issues etc being able to synthesize all
that we've been being able to develop a
platform where people can upload
personal data that is synthesized with
it you know unique kind of a I like
combinatorial algorithms they can then
be able to direct people to what
technologies have the highest
probability of being most meaningful for
them for the kinds of things they're
wanting to work on and then being able
to have a deeper version of that
available for medical practitioners
really pioneering the future of
personalized medicine where we can
synthesize all of the diagnostics and
synthesize all the therapeutics
customize the therapeutics based on this
kind of deeper interpretive model and so
we don't say too much about that yet
because you know one should share about
the things as we were able to release
meaningful offerings but if you keep it
checking in we will see more monthly
terrific well thank you very much for
explaining the difference between no
tropics smart drugs and brain nutrients
is a fascinating conversation I'm going
to make sure that my farmers market down
on let's see what's what wrote is it on
if it's on Santa Monica Boulevard it
might be on something else actually
there's a farmers market that I've been
meaning to go to but I don't go to it
because I take the lazy route I must hit
that now hit that now and start asking
the types of questions that you have
that you encouraged me to us so I
appreciate that thank you very much for
sharing your experience Daniel I really
appreciate that if you're listening make
sure you like the neuro Hector gyro
hacker collective Facebook page and you
can go and check out more at neuro
hacker.com thank you sir for you Tom I
appreciate a Daniel seems I'm really
happy to see all of the important
empowering brilliant work you're sharing
with people and to delight to be on here
thank you thank you sir